<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe and true relation of the murther of Mr. Thomas Scott preacher of Gods word and Batchelor of Diuinitie. Committed by Iohn Lambert souldier of the garrison of Vtricke, the 18. of Iune. 1626. With his examination, confession, and execution.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103203</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838960</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838960</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3353</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3353)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1219:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe and true relation of the murther of Mr. Thomas Scott preacher of Gods word and Batchelor of Diuinitie. Committed by Iohn Lambert souldier of the garrison of Vtricke, the 18. of Iune. 1626. With his examination, confession, and execution.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by M. Flesher] for Nath. Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 259) on title page.</note>
                  <note>Title page and page 10 marked and stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trials (Murder) --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3353:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3353:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE AND TRVE RELATION OF THE MVRTHER of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> THOMAS SCOTT Preacher of Gods Word and Batchelor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>Committed by <hi>John Lambert</hi> Souldier of the Garriſon of
<hi>Vtricke,</hi> the 18. <hi>of Iune.</hi> 1626.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With his Examination, Confeſsion, and Execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Butter.</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:3353:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3353:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A briefe and true Relation of the Murther of Maſter
<hi>Thomas Scott.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt many diſaſtrous events and cruell murthers which haue lately happened in theſe parts, no one is ſo lamentable; at that which was commited vpon Sunday laſt being the 18. of Iune, 1626. by one <hi>Iohn Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert.</hi> His father (hee ſaid) had beene ſometimes Maſter of a ſhip, and his mother was a Gentlewoman, borne in <hi>Warwickeſhire,</hi> and liued and died neere <hi>Tower-hill</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> where hee was borne. Himſelf had beene brought vp with a Merchant of Wine in
<hi>London;</hi> and for a while was his Factor in <hi>France,</hi> where he learned the language perfectly. But his eſtate failing him, in the end was forced to betake him to Armes, and follow the warre. Hee was at this time aged thirty and ſixe yeares, of a tall ſtature, and well clothed.</p>
            <div type="body_of_account">
               <head>The Murther was in this manner committed.</head>
               <p>Maſter <hi>Scot</hi> who had preached in the forenoone, and in the afternoone about two of the clocke comming to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church to performe the exerciſe of that <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3353:3"/>day, was accompanied with his brother Maſter <hi>William Scott,</hi> (that was come but 7. dayes before out of <hi>England</hi> to ſee his brother) and with his Newhew <hi>Thomas Scott.</hi> Maſter <hi>Scott</hi> comming betwixt them both, &amp; approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neere vnto the Church yard; <hi>Lambert</hi> who had fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe by 12. of the clock at the Churchyard gate to attend his comming, eſpying him draw nigh, roſe vp from his fear, and made towards them, drew his Rapier (which he had purpoſely ſharpned) &amp; put in a thruſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his heart. But his brother perceiuing the thruſt ſo neere, which the lappe of his cloake beat it a little downewards: and it entred through a skirt of his doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and waſtband of his hoſe into his be ly. Whereupon falling downe hee was raiſed vp againe by his brother, and nephew, betwixt whom he was.</p>
               <p>This being done, <hi>Lambert</hi> ſought by flight to haue eſcaped, but he was preſently apprehended, &amp; brought backe to Maſter
<hi>Scott;</hi> who told him he had neuer of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him, and asked him what reaſon had moued him to ſo wicked a fact.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lambert</hi> very audaciouſly and inſolently replyed; that what he had done, he would anſwer; And that he was a Traitor to his Soueraigne, and had iniured him by hindring his preferment to the Queene of
<hi>Bohemia.</hi> Maſter <hi>Scott</hi> replied, I know thee not, God forgiue thee and I doe from the bottome of my heart.</p>
               <p>The rumor hereof was preſently brought into the Church, by the Readers wife co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in with an open exclamation; Whereupon all the people ran forth much amazed and confuſed, and ſome of them drawing their ſwords, would haue ſlaine <hi>Lambert.</hi> But <hi>Monſ: Van Hilton</hi> Secretarie of the States, and others there preſent perſwaded them to put vp their ſwords, and to let Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice paſſe vpon him. <hi>Lambert</hi> was preſently brought to priſon; and Maſter <hi>Scott,</hi> went himſelfe to Mr. <hi>Iames Nelthorpe</hi> the Chirurgian his houſe, and all this while
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3353:3"/>was of good courage. After his wound was ſearched he ſaid, Maſter <hi>Iames</hi> what thinke you? I hope it will ſoone be healed; but Maſter <hi>Iames</hi> ſhaked his head, and replied nothing to him, which Maſter <hi>Scott</hi> perceiuing anſwered himſelfe, Then muſt I prepare my ſelfe for God, and for death. And theſe were the laſt words hee ſpake, who was preſently caried home in a chaire, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clad, laid in his bed, and about one houre after dyed, which was about foure of the clocke in the afternoone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lambert</hi> all this while made no ſhew of any ſorrow; but moſt impudently affirmed (as it were triumphing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) That if it were to be done, hee could yet doe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; making a fond and vaine ſhew of hope of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, which hee perſwaded himſelfe of, by an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, or rather a Satanicall illuſion, which had thus blinded &amp; ſeduced him thereunto. For, after-wards very often hee publiquely affirmed vnto all that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred with him, and more eſpecially to the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the garriſon, and the Preacher that went vnto him to ſtir him vp to repentance: That hee knew they all could not hurt him; For, ſaith he, my heauens, my Miſtris, the ſpirits of my Soueraigne in the Queene of <hi>Bohemia</hi> will free me preſently. And calling for pen and inke to write vnto her, hee there write ſomething to no purpoſe, and then the penne and inke was taken from him.</p>
               <p>In this blinded and ſeduced opinion of his owne worth, of that good deed, (as he termed it) and of the inſurie which Maſter <hi>Scott</hi> had done vnto him, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued all the next day: adding other circumſtances thereunto, how that the reſolution to doe this damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fact, had beene taken about eight weekes before: And that his ſpirits had vrged and enforced him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. And he confeſſed that the Sunday before hee had feared himſelfe in the ſame place thinking then to haue killed him; but hee was by an euill ſpirit caried <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3353:4"/>vnto the towne walls, and with that ſpirit guarded to his lodging where it left him, and that preſently after in his lodging he was aſſaulted by many good ſpirits, (as he called them) who would giue him no eaſe night nor day, vntill that deed ſhould be performed; and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him that Maſter
<hi>Scott</hi> alone was the cauſe of the hinderance of his preferment, and aduancement; And that as ſoone as he ſhould be ſlaine, then his aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould preſently follow.</p>
               <p>With theſe, and many other fond reaſons, he harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned himſelfe, and to the Sergeant Maior of the Gariſon, hee affirmed that the fact was iuſt, lawfull, according to Gods word, and the law of
<hi>Moſes,</hi> which by Scrip-he would iuſtifie; For, (ſaith he) confirme that law of <hi>Lex talionis,</hi> he might recompence one euill deed with another, as an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth,  and then he had done but Iuſtice, for which no law could conuince or condemne him.</p>
               <p>In this ſeduced and blinded obſtinacie, he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till Tueſday at night: For, all the exhortations and admonitions that could be vſed to him could nothing at all preuaile with him. Now the next day after the fact was done, hee being onely examined, and hauing anſwered as is aforeſaid: his examinations were by the preſent commander of the garriſon (Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>William Droumownd</hi> Segeant Maior of a Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Regiment, ſent vnto <hi>Vienna,</hi> to the Gouernour, the Baron of <hi>Brederode,</hi> who by poſte ſent them to the Prince. from whom came anſwer backe againe vpon the tueſday following to proceed in Iuſtice againſt him according as the nature of his fact did require. Which by ſharpe examination vpon the racke was effected on Wedneſday following.</p>
               <p>A little before which time he began to haue ſome fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the fact, and a kind of ſorrow for the ſame; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring the ayde of the Officers to labour for his releaſe, <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3353:4"/>and ſaid to be well contented to offer his right hand for ſais faction for the deed, ſo that his life might be ſpared. And yet euen at the very inſtant of his torture would not bee perſwaded but that his heauens, and his Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne (who daily and hourely had termed him one of heauens worthies, and heauens elect, and many the like epithites) would free him, and not ſuffer him to bee hurt, but found the contrary.</p>
               <p>Afterwards he confeſſed further, that hee entended often to haue acquainted Maſter <hi>Scott</hi> with theſe temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to haue reuealed the ſame, but conſidering that by ſome meanes or other it might be knowne; and for which the ſouldiers would haue raiſed ieſts, &amp; mocked and leered him there with, he therefore held his reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And moreouer vpon the racke, and afterwards being charged, that he was hired to doe this deed, and deſired that he would reveale the truth, who they were that had ſet him on in this action: Hee very ſeriouſly proteſted, that although he had ſerued the en emie for the ſpace of three moneths or thereabouts vnder a Scotch Captaine before <hi>Bergenvp Zome</hi> the time of that ſiege, and afterwards a while in garriſon in <hi>Flanders;</hi> yet he himſelfe was neuer any Papiſt; And that hee was not ſet on, nor hired, by any Prieſt, Ieſuit or other whatſoeuer; But that the ſpirit had perſwaded him of the iniuries as is aforeſaid, and that hee could haue no reſt vntill that fact was performed.</p>
               <p>He affirmed likewiſe that hee neuer miſſed the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Maſter <hi>Scotts</hi> Sermons; and that very often hee had heard him preach vnto his good content, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and comfort.</p>
               <p>The ſame wedneſday was Maſter <hi>Scott</hi> buried in
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricht,</hi> after a very honourable manner; accompanied with all the Miniſters, Elders, and Deacons of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Congregations; with the Deputies of the States of <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3353:5"/>the Prouince, and moſt of the Magiſtrates of the towne in mourning cloakes; with a traine of Burgers, and the Commanders, Captaines, Officers and Souldiers of the Garriſons, the like hath not beene ſeene, nor knowne in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricht;</hi> with a generall lamentation of all men for the loſſe of ſo worthy a man.</p>
               <p>The day following, the Councell of Warre aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to determine the ſentence, who there a greed that the offender ſhould bee Raiebracht, that is, to haue his bones broken vpon a wheele, and ſo to be ſet vp by the ordinarie place of Iuſtice; which, when <hi>Lambert</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, with an earneſt deſire he intreated that his body might bee buried. Vpon this his intreatie, that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was altered, and it was reſolued, that the next day his right hand ſhould be cut off, and nailed to the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, then he to be hanged, and his dead body to bee laid vpon a wheele without any buriall.</p>
               <p>The ſame euening the Preacher, and other godly men being ſent vnto him, to giue him warning and to prepare him for death: They found him as vncapable of inſtruction, and as full of his fond and imaginarie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits as before; Then likewiſe affirming that his Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, who daily and hourely appeared vnto him as the ſpirit of the late Queene
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> in the Queene of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the ſpirit of his Soueraigne King <hi>Iames,</hi> and of his Excellency the late Prince of
<hi>Orange;</hi> by whom he was intituled one of Heauens Worthies, Heauens Elect, &amp;c. And from theſe vaine fantaſies he could not bee brought neither by threatning of his temporall death, nor of his ſoules damnation hereafter. Hee continued in this obſtinacie, and obdurateneſſe, 09 notwithſtanding whatſoeuer promiſes, or threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings could bee ſpoken vnto him concerning his ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or damnation. In all other diſcourſes, whereof there were ſundry both in Engliſh and in good French,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3353:5"/>he was very ſenſible, able enough, &amp; prompt, and held a good formalitie therein, to the admiration of many that were ſent and heard him.</p>
               <p>At the place of execution there was no alteration in him, His right hand was firſt cut off, and nailed to the gallowes; And after that the Preacher had exhorted him, and prayed with him, he was hanged. And very ſeldome hath it beene ſeene that a man ſhould liue ſo long as he did hanging, though the Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner did the beſt he could to helpe to rid him out of his paine.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3353:6"/>
            <head>A Funerall Elegie vpon the vntimely and much bewailed death of that <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Preacher of Gods Word</hi> Mr. THOMAS SCOTT, ſlaine vpon Sunday the 18. of Iune, 1626. Stilo veteri.</head>
            <l>SVch is hells rage againſt Gods ſonnes, Gods Saints,</l>
            <l>Such good mens wrongs; ſuch are their paines and plaints</l>
            <l>Whileſt they liue here; Such wicked mens deſpight</l>
            <l>Againſt Gods Word, that Word of power and might;</l>
            <l>They ioyne with hell their bodies here to ſlay,</l>
            <l>Who ioyne with God to ſave their ſoules for aye.</l>
            <l>They ſtop their breath who pray to Gods good Spirit,</l>
            <l>To breath into their ſoules <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſauing merit.</l>
            <l>With ſwords deviding their two darling twinnes,</l>
            <l>Who with Gods Word divide their ſoules and ſinnes:</l>
            <l>Witneſſe this corps, this ſacrificed Saint,</l>
            <l>Whom none of crime, none could of wrong attaint.</l>
            <l>Yet on Gods day vpon Gods Word attending,</l>
            <l>By curſed hands his bleſſed daies had ending.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3353:6"/>
            <head>Another.</head>
            <l>MAns life' s a warfare, wayfare. Ah good man</l>
            <l>Thou foundſt it true; Thy words, thy writings can</l>
            <l>Witneſſe to all, inflamed with true Zeale</l>
            <l>To God, to Church, to King, to Commonweale,</l>
            <l>Armed with valor, to thine eternall praiſe</l>
            <l>Thou warr' dſt againſt the monſters of our daies;</l>
            <l>Oppos' d great gyants ſinnes, great ſinners hence</l>
            <l>Warr' d againſt thee, and wronged thy innocence.</l>
            <l>From Warre to wayfare thou did' ſt runne thy race</l>
            <l>In warlike lands diſpoſing time and place,</l>
            <l>To Gods great glory, and the Churches good,</l>
            <l>Till helliſh hands exhauſted thy hearts blood.</l>
            <l>Well, t'was Gods will who had decreed it beſt</l>
            <l>To call thee from thy labor to his reſt.</l>
            <l>Then farewell father, mounted from mortall eyne,</l>
            <l>Such was thy life, I wiſh my ſoule with thine.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="authentication">
            <head>Certificate.</head>
            <p>THe Souldier (named <hi>Iohn Lambert,</hi> the Preachers name was M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Scott</hi>) watching his opportunity murthered him, and publikely examined at <hi>Vtricht,</hi> on the racke, and after, made this vaine &amp; ridiculous relation, That the ſpirit his Miſtris, the heauens elect, the favorite to Q <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth</hi> the late Queene of
<hi>England,</hi> whoſe ſpirit tranſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grated into her Maieſty the Queene of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> which Q. of <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſo fauored him, that ſhe entended to receiue <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3353:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3353:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3353:8"/>him into her ſeruice.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd conſidering with himſelfe why he was not entertained into her ſervice, a ſpirit ſuggeſted to him, that M. <hi>Scott</hi> hindred him, and vntill ſuch time as the ſaid M. <hi>Scott</hi> was killed, he ſhould not bee entertained into his Maieſties ſeruice. Whereupon, he was reſolued to kill him; He confeſſed alſo that he was neuer hired or induced, by the perſwaſions of any Prieſt, Ieſuit, or any other perſon to attempt this bloody act. He was twice racked &amp; whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped on the racke; At which time of his racking and whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and at other times of his priuate and publike exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, yea euen to his death, he continued in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid confeſſion, avouching and ſolemnely proteſting, on his hope of ſaluation, the naked &amp; whole truth of his ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. That this was the ſumme and ſubſtance of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, we whoſe names are hereunder written, doe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and in the word of truth, ſincerely witneſſe &amp; teſtifie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ieremiah Elborough <hi>Paſtor of the</hi> Engliſh
<hi>Church at</hi> Vtricht, <hi>who was preſent at his Confeſſion vpon the racke, and at his death.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>I whoſe name is here vnderwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Commander of the right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Lord Viſcount</hi> Wimble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>his foot Company, was likewiſe at the ſaid</hi> Lamberts <hi>Confeſſion both before and at his death, who on the racke proteſted as is aboue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. This is truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Hv: HANKINSON.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <pb facs="tcp:3353:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
